Preliminary Guide to the Allan H. Gilbert Papers, 1926-1976
Allan H. Gilbert papers 1926-1976
Gilbert, Allan H., 1888-
12.56 Linear Feet 11,525 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Allan H. Gilbert Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1994.
Biographical Note
Professor of English at Duke University, specialist in Renaissance Italy.
Collection Overview
Manuscripts, research files, correspondence, approximately 1287 black-and-white photographs and photostats of documents from various repositories and used in his research, and 3 reels of microfilm. Subjects of the research files and manuscripts include: Dante, Machiavelli, Milton, Jonson, and Aristotle (his POETICS).
Addition (2007-0141; 400 items, 0.5 lin. ft.) contains index files documenting the Gilbert's book collection. Many of these books are now in the collection at the Rare Book, Manuscript and Sepcial Collections Library at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Gilbert, Allan H.,; 1888-
Dante Alighieri,; 1265-1321.
Milton, John,; 1608-1674.
Machiavelli, Niccolò,; 1469-1527.
Jonson, Ben,; 1573?-1637.
Homer
Aristotle
Aristotle; Poetics.
Black-and-white photographs
Microfilms
Stats.
Contents of Collection
- Accession 1994-0081
  - Professional Correspondence, (10 folders) (Box 1)
  - Academic Work
    - Ariosto and Machiavelli, (14 folders)
  - Academic Work (cont.) (Box 2)
    - Ariosto and Machievelli, (36 folders)
      - Literary Manuscripts, Reproductions
        - Boiardo CF 1049, photo-reproduction, (2 folders)
        - Cinque Canti - Codex Toddei, (2 folders)
        - OF 1.1 -24.110, photocopy
        - OF 24.110 - 46. last, photocopy
  - Academic Work (cont.) (Box 3)
    - [English] Renaissance Literature and Art, (26 folders)
    - [Classical Literature and Poetics], (13 folders)
  - Academic Work (cont.) (Box 4)
    - Poetics, (28 folders)
    - Orlando Furioso, (6 folders)
    - Machiavelli: Photos of early editions, (3 folders)
  - Academic Work (cont.) (Box 5)
    - Machiavelli: Photos of early editions cont., (5 folders)
    - Orlando Furioso, (17 folders)
    - Poetics, (9 folders)
  - Academic Work (cont.) (Box 6)
    - Poetics (cont.), (39 folders)
    - Text of Cinque Canti 1.69, (Index cards, 2 boxes)
    - Orlando Furioso March '55, vol. 2 of Debenedetti, Microfilm, (3 reels)
  - Academic Work (cont.) (Box 7)
    - Machievelli: Photos of early editions, (2 folders)
    - Ariosto, photos of mss., (3 folders)
    - [Il Testo de Cinque Canti]
  - Academic Work (cont.) (Box 8)
    - Vincent de Beauvois, De Morale Principis Institutione, photos of mss.
    - Trinity College Cambridge, ms. No. 347(8)
    - Ryland's Furioso, photos of mss., (4 folders)
  - Acedemic Work (cont.) (Box 9)
    - Castruccio
    - Cinque Canti Variants- Ribbon Copy (empty)
    - Cinque Canti Variants- Anna maria's Version
      English Rejected, copy 3 of copy Anna Maria, 1957 October, Carbon as sent to Laterza
    - The Frick Collection Veronese Wisdom and Strength
    - Florentine Portraits
    - stats
      - A
      - B
      - C
      - D
      - G
      - H
    - Ariosto 5 Canti and Composition, (two folders)
    - La Poesia (complete carbon with revision by Panope's notes), (three folders)
    - Virtues II (empty)
    - Metrics of P(aradise) Lost
    - Poesia Postille Carbon, (three folders)
    - Madison Papers
    - [Machiavelli]
    - Victory Winged Nat'l Musemn, Naples; Victory Winged Nat'l Musemn; Victory of Samothrace, Louvre
    - Urania (See Edgar Wind) Astronomy Campanile del Duomo, Firenze
    - Venus, Birth.
      Rubens, Musée Royal de Bruxelles. See Johnson Collection: Venus and Vulcan
    - [Letters]
    - [Raccomandate]
    - Manoscritto Senza Lettera
    - MLA 1947
      Leopere Minore Di Ariosto. In Writing Should Use Subjunctive After I Think, I believe
    - Lettera
    - 2 Negromante
    - Translation of 2 Negromante
    - Monuments
      S. Mara Del Popolo, Rome (Virtues Shown); Chiesa di S. Domenico, Bologna( Virtues Shown); Chiesa Di S. Agostino, San Gimignano, by B. Da Maiano (Virtues Shown); Castel Nuovo, Naples, Arco dii Trionfo del Re Alfonso I. D' Aragona
    - Virtues IV, Venetian Lace, Hope, Temperance
    - Winds, See Edgar Wind( empty)
    - Tarquin and Lucretia, by Titian
    - Bronze Head of Persephone 4th Century B.C., Syracus
      Persephone and Pluto (Frenth Translation of Ovid, 1539). See Pluto, also Devil
    - Orpheus and Eurydice, paris Psalter
    - Nymph (River)
      by fountain (wearing necklace, bracelet, and a lawn) Cranack?
    - San Marco, Piazza, See Blue Venezia (empty)
    - Silenve, Rubens
      Dancing Faun. Nat'l Museum, Naples. See Edgar Wind: Satyr, Bacchus; See Johnson Collection: Faun, Silenvs
    - 5 Canti, (six folders)
    - Of Variants Ribbon on Text of Cinque Canti
      Rough Copy Corrected to 1956 August 8
    - Anna Marias' Translation for Cinque Canti
    - Hercules in His Bowl (Michigan)
      cf. Bacon and Jonson and Herymick (Sp?)
    - Armor Stibbert
    - Croce Bulletin etc (not all here), 1961 February 14
    - Tobit
      Botticelli, Florence, Savoldo, Borghese Gallery, Filippino Lippi, Kress Collection, Titian, Venice, Chiesa di San Marziale
- Accession 1994-096
  - Academic Work (Box 1)
    - Peacham, (7 folders)
    - Professional Correspondence
    - Greek Manuscript, photo-reproduction (Box 2)
- Accession (2007-0141), 1 Box
  Addition (400 items, 0.5 lin. ft.) contains index files documenting the Gilbert's book collection. Many of these books are now in the collection at the Rare Book, Manuscript and Sepcial Collections Library at Duke University.
  - Card index files (Box 1)